Campus Action; Records apap164
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Campus Action Records
1992-2006
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Campus Action (Albany, N.Y.)
apap164
2.29 cubic ft. and 68 mb of electronic records (size before being reformatted to PDF files)
Campus Action was formed in April of 1992 as a multi-cultural, multi-issue organization with a mission to promote activism and support activist organizations on university campuses in New Yorks Capital Region.
Administrative History
Campus Action was formed in April of 1992 as a multi-cultural, multi-issue organization with a mission to promote activism and support activist organizations on university campuses in New York's Capital Region. It maintained eight chapters representing individual campuses as well as a central office at the Social Justice Center in Albany. Campus Action was led by David Easter, the founder and coordinator, and a board of directors. The campus chapters in the Capital Region, including the University at Albany, possessed considerable autonomy.
The primary goal of Campus Action was to increase progressive activism on college campuses and build cooperation between campus and community activist groups. To this end, it produced a number of publications, including guidebooks for organizing, specific issue guides on racism and sexism, and directories of activist groups. Its most regular publication was the Campus Action News newsletter, an update of activities and events, published three times a year. Campus Action offered internships to students interested in working for an activist organization and published an Alternative Internship Directory that directed students to other organizations. In addition, Campus Action sponsored and organized a number of events including a biannual organizing conference for a variety of causes, workshops, protests, and demonstrations.
In April of 2006, David Easter announced that he was stepping down as coordinator of Campus Action and closing the central office. This meant that publication of Campus Action News would cease and the website would no longer be maintained, but the individual campus chapters would continue to function.
Scope and Contents
The records of Campus Action contain materials collected and generated by the organization including both paper documents and electronic records. These materials include minutes, correspondence, publications, grant applications, webpages, fliers, leaflets and other handouts. The collection holds material from the Campus Action central office and does not contain material specific to the individual chapters of Campus Action.
Campus Action created a number of publications for campus distribution. These include the newsletter Campus Action News, two study guides, and directories of local activist organizations and internships. These are all well represented in the collection, along with materials from the biannual conferences held to help organize activism, primarily as paper documents with some additional later material in electronic form. There is a lack of records from 2000 when David Easter was on hiatus and, for example, there were no issues of Campus Action News produced.
The central office collected a great deal of material on issues of interest to Campus Action, including acquaintance rape, racism, war protest, feminism, and civil liberties. The paper materials deal heavily with the issue of date rape and sexual harassment on campus, while the more extensive electronic files include more recent material on a wider variety of topics. All electronic records were reformatted to Printable Document Format (PDF) files and can be viewed with Adobe Acrobat Reader.
Campus Action's opposition to the wars in Afghanistan and Iraq is particularly well documented in the electronic records, with related defenses of detainees in the civil rights and racism sections. The case of Ali Yaghi is also documented in the electronic records. Yaghi, an Albany resident and owner of a pizza shop, was arrested just days after 9/11. He was detained on the basis of a tip by a passerby, who claimed to have heard Yaghi making anti-American statements. Yaghi was detained for months and though eventually cleared of all allegations related to terrorism, he was deported to his native Jordan because of his immigration status.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Series 1: Administrative Files, 1992-2004, undated
Series 2: Publications, 1992-2006, undated
Series 3: Events, 1992-2004, undated
Series 4: Subject Files, 1993-2003, undated
Series arrangement statement: SUNY will complete.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Campus Action in July and September 2003, May and June 2004, and April 2006.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Military and Armed Conflict; Human Sexuality and Gender Identity; Education; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Conservation and the Environment; Albany, New York; Students--New York (State)--Political activity.; Demonstrations--New York (State); Peace movements--New York (State); Sex discrimination against women--New York (State); Acquaintance rape--New York (State); Gay rights--New York (State); Sweatshops--New York (State); Conservation of natural resources--New York (State); Yaghi, Ali.; Campus Action (Albany, N.Y.)
- Administrative Files, 1992-2004; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of records generated by Campus Action directly pertaining to its administrative functions, either on paper or stored on the hard drive of the main computer. Included are meeting agendas, minutes, memoranda, and organizational records such as by-laws and procedures. In addition, the series includes materials related to several fundraising methods explored by Campus Action, from holding dances to applying for grants. This series contains some correspondence, but this largely consists of mailings to members and related organizations rather than internal correspondence.
  The electronic files include several spreadsheets that have been converted to PDF format. This allows them to be viewed, but the nature of the format has split some of the longer columns in ways that render them difficult to read. In addition, four databases cannot be converted without sacrificing their functionality. Contact a staff member for further information.
  - Board, 1993-1997; 2002; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Board, Introductory Packet, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Board, Introductory Packet, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - By-laws, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Chapters, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Chapters, University at Albany, 1993-1994; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Contact Lists, 1997-1998; 2004; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1993-1997; 2002; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Finance Committee, Minutes, 1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Fundraising, Dance-a-thon, 1996-1997; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Fundraising, Grants, 1997-1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Fundraising, House Parties, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Fundraising, Mailing to University at Albany Faculty, Correspondence, Notes, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Fundraising, Phone Banking, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Fundraising, United Way, 1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
  - Long Range Planning, 1995; 2002; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 16)
  - Mailings, 1997-1999; 2002-2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 17)
  - Meeting Minutes, Agendas, 1992-1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 18)
  - Meeting Minutes, Agendas, 1996-2003 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 19)
  - Membership Committee, 2002; Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Membership Drive, 1992-1993; Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Membership Renewal, Correspondence, Contact Lists, 1995-1997; Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Memoranda, 1994-1995; 1997-1998 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Structure and Procedures, 1992 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Sustaining Members, Contact Lists, Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Agenda and Minutes, Agenda, 2002
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2001
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2001
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2001
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2001
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2002
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2002
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2002
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2002
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2002
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2002
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2002
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2002
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2003
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2003
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, 2003
  - Agenda and Minutes, Minutes, Board Planning Session, 2002
  - Board Contract, 2002
  - Board List, 2002
  - By-laws, 2002
  - Budget Reports, Campus Action Budget, 2003
  - Budget Reports, Campus Action Yearly Budget, 2001-2002
  - Budget Reports, Campus Action Yearly Budget, 2002
  - Budget Reports, Campus Action Yearly Budget (30,000), 2002-2003
  - Budget Reports, Campus Action Organizational Chart, 2002
  - Chapters, Chapter Relations, Chapter Contacts, 2002
  - Chapters, Chapter Relations, Chapter-CA relation, 2001
  - Chapters, Chapter Relations, Contact List For Chapters, 2003
  - Chapters, Chapter Relations, Contacts For Campus Action Chapters, 2003
  - Chapters, Chapter Relations, How Campus Action Chapters Function, 2002
  - Chapters, Chapter Relations, Upcoming Events and Activities for Campus Action Chapters, 2003
  - Chapters, RPI, RPI Email List, 2004
  - Chapters, Sage, Sage Students, 2003
  - Chapters, Siena, Siena Chapter Report, 2003
  - Chapters, Siena, Siena Email List, 2002
  - Chapters, Siena, Meeting Poster, 2002
  - Chapters, Siena, Website, 2002
  - Chapters, St. Rose, Activism On The St. Rose Campus, 2004
  - Chapters, St. Rose, St. Rose Faculty Phone List, 2001
  - Chapters, SUNY, SUNY Student List 2, 2003
  - Chapters, Union, Union College Campus Action, 2004
  - Chapters, Union, Union College Student Groups, 2002
  - Correspondence, Benjamin Mergelsberg Letter, 2001
  - Correspondence, Berenson Lawyer Speaking Info, 2001
  - Correspondence, Board Membership Letter, 2002
  - Correspondence, Fund Letter, 2002
  - Correspondence, Fund Letter, 2004
  - Correspondence, Fundraising Letter, 2001
  - Correspondence, Fundraising Letter, 2001
  - Correspondence, Fundraising Letter, 2002
  - Correspondence, Fundraising Letter, 2002
  - Correspondence, Fundraising Letter, 2003
  - Correspondence, Fundraising Letter, 2003
  - Correspondence, Fundraising Letter, 2003
  - Correspondence, Fundraising Letter, 2004
  - Correspondence, IRS Substantiation Letter, 2004
  - Correspondence, Labor Religion Invitation Letter, 2002
  - Correspondence, Membership Renewal Letter, 1996
  - Correspondence, New York State Withholding Department, 2002
  - Correspondence, Postal Permit Application Letter, 2001
  - Correspondence, Social Justice Center Letter, 2001
  - Correspondence, Social Justice Center Letter, 2001
  - Correspondence, Thank You Letter, 2004
  - Correspondence, Unitarian Letter, 2003
  - Correspondence, Walter Board Contract Letter, 2002
  - Databases and Spreadsheets, Activist Directory, 2003
  - Databases and Spreadsheets, Activist Directory Community Groups, 2002
  - Databases and Spreadsheets, Activist Directory Student Groups, 2002
  - Databases and Spreadsheets, Budget 30,000, 2002
  - Databases and Spreadsheets, Campus Action Grants Received, 2002
  - Databases and Spreadsheets, Copy of Campus Action News, 2002
  - Databases and Spreadsheets, Foundation Spreadsheet, 2002
  - Grants, Boehm Foundation Inquiry Letter, 2002
  - Grants, Cover Letter, 2002
  - Grants, Cover Letter, 2003
  - Grants, Foundation Prospects, 2002
  - Grants, Grantee Fiscal And Progress Report, 2003
  - Grants, Holding Our Own Application, 2001
  - Grants, List Foundation Inquiry Letter, 2001
  - Grants, List Foundation Questions, 2001
  - Grants, Overcoming Racism Project Budget, 2003
  - Grants, Peace Development Fund Proposal, 2001
  - Grants, Regular Grant Application, 2003
  - Grants, Resist Actual Application, 2003
  - Grants, Resist Application, 2003
  - Grants, Resist Multi-year Application, 2002
  - Grants, Resist Multi-year Application Questions (Answers), 2002
  - Grants, Resist Proposal, 2002
  - Grants, Resist References, 2002
  - Grants, Tides Application, 2002
  - Grants, Tides Application Short, 2002
  - Membership Recruitment, Fundraising Role Memo, 2002
  - Membership Recruitment, Membership Recommendations, Joeanna, 2002
  - Membership Recruitment, Membership Recommendation, Laura, 2002
  - Membership Recruitment, Membership Committee Meeting Minutes, 2002
  - Membership Recruitment, Membership Recruitment Plan, 2002
  - Structure and Procedures, 2002
  - Campus Action Database, 2004
  - Colleges Northeast, 2001
  - Media, 2004
  - Peace Action List, 2004
- Publications, 1992-2006; Undated; 2
  Arranged by alphabetically.
  This series includes the variety of publications generated by Campus Action. These include the major publications of Campus Action, such as the Campus Action News newsletter, the Activist Directory, and the Alternative Internship Directory. In some cases these publications consist of the original master copies created for photocopying. When a final version of a publication was available, it was retained instead of these master copies. This series also includes numerous fliers, individual subject guides, conference materials, leaflets, and other handouts intended for campus distribution.
  - Activist Directory, 1993-1999; Undated (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 1)
  - Alternative Internship Directory, 1995-1999; 2002; Undated (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 2)
  - Articles, News Clippings, 1997; Undated (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 3)
  - Campus Action Network Organizing Guide, Undated (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 4)
  - Campus Action News, 1992-1995; 1997-1999 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 5)
  - Campus Action News, 2001-2006 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 6)
  - Campus Action Syndicated Column, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 7)
  - Fliers, 1995-1997; Undated (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 8)
  - Leaflets, Pamphlets, 1998; 2002; Undated (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 9)
  - Networking Conferences, Conference Materials, 1992-1993; Undated (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 10)
  - Organizing Packet, 1995; 1998; Undated (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 11)
  - "Organizing Tips and Resources", Undated (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 12)
  - Recognizing Racism Study Guide, 2002; Undated (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 13)
  - Speakers and Program Guide, 1997-1999; Undated (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 14)
  - Student Environmental Network, Article, Directory, Fliers, Undated (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 15)
  - Activist Directory, 2002 Slip
  - Activist Directory, Activist Directory, 2001
  - Activist Directory, Activist Directory Community Version, 2002
  - Activist Directory, Activist Directory Questionnaire, 2003
  - Activist Directory, Activist Directory Student Groups By Campus, 2002
  - Activist Directory, Brochure For Listed Groups, 2002
  - Activist Directory, Directory Update Letter, 2004
  - Activist Directory, RPI Contacts, 2001
  - Activist Directory, Skidmore Contacts, 2003
  - Activist Directory, Union Directory Groups, 2002
  - Activist Directory, Update Letter, 2003
  - Campus Action Brochure, 2001
  - Campus Action News, Campus Action News #19, 1998 September
  - Campus Action News, Campus Action News #20, 1999 February
  - Campus Action News, Campus Action News #21, 2001 October
  - Campus Action News, Campus Action News #22, 2002 February
  - Campus Action News, Campus Action News #23, 2002 April
  - Campus Action News, Campus Action News #24, 2002 September
  - Campus Action News, Campus Action News #25, 2003 February
  - Campus Action News, Campus Action News #26, 2003 April
  - Campus Action News, Campus Action News #27, 2003 September
  - Campus Action News, Campus Action News #28, 2004 January
  - Campus Action News, Campus Action News #29, 2004 April
  - Media List, 2001
  - Media List, 2003
  - Organizing Guide Frontpage, 2003
  - Organizing Guide Intro & Index, 2003
  - Recognizing Racism Study Guide, Action Ideas To Fight Racism, 2002
  - Recognizing Racism Study Guide, Discussion Questions On Recognizing Racism, 2002
  - Recognizing Racism Study Guide, Study Guide, 2003
  - Recognizing Racism Study Guide, Study Guide Cover, 2002
  - Report 2002-2003
  - Student Activism Study Guide, Campaigning For Change At St. Rose, 2002
  - Student Activism Study Guide, Higher Education Opportunity Program Student Press Literature, 2002
  - Student Activism Study Guide, Issues And Tactics For Campus Activists, 2002
  - Student Activism Study Guide, Multicultural Demands At Union College, 2002
  - Student Activism Study Guide, SUNY Students Takeover President's Office, 2002
  - Student Activism Study Guide, Workshop Timeline, 2002
  - Website, 2006 April 28
- Events, 1992-2004; Undated; 3
  This series contains records generated for events sponsored and organized by Campus Action. These events are primarily conferences, including the biannual conference held by Campus Action as well as other conferences in which Campus Action participated. Paper materials usually include some form of sign-in sheet, notes, schedules, correspondence, fliers, leaflets, and other handouts. Electronic documents include more of the same, along with lists of all attendees.
  - "Becoming Anti-Racist Activists", Conference, February 2002, Conference Materials (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 1)
  - "Beyond Part Politics: Gathering Voices for Social Change", Conference, Conference Materials, 2004 (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 2)
  - Black Students Communications Organizing Meeting (BSCOM), 1998 (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 3)
  - "Building Strong Organizations", Conference, October 2002, Conference Materials, 2003 (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 4)
  - "Building the Peace Movement", Meeting, Flier, Schedule, Transparencies, 2003 (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 5)
  - "Campus Action for Human Rights", Conference, September 1996, Conference Materials (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 6)
  - "Continuing the Movement", Conference, October 1993, Conference Material (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 7)
  - Cynthia Barans Speech, Correspondence, Fliers, Notes, 2003 (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 8)
  - Detainees, Guantnamo Bay Naval Base, Panel, 2004 (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 9)
  - "Get Your Hands Up!" Conference, October 1998, Conference Materials (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 10)
  - "Grassroots Student Organizing", Conference, October 1997, Conference Materials (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 11)
  - "Inter-Campus Sexual Assault", Conference, Conference Materials, 1996 (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 12)
  - Labor Teach-In, Correspondence, Article, Notes, 1997 (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 13)
  - March Against War and Occupation, Correspondence, 2004 (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 14)
  - March to Save Women's Lives, Correspondence, Registration Forms, Minutes, 2004 (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 15)
  - "Naked Acts" Showing, 1997-1998; Undated (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 16)
  - Noa Simone and Hossein Alizaden Speech, Flier, News Clipping, Schedule, 2002 (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 17)
  - "Organizing for Change", Conference, October 1995, Conference Materials (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 18)
  - "Organizing for Social Change", Workshop, Undated (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 19)
  - School of Americas Speaking Tour, Correspondence, Fliers, 2005 (Box 1 (3-Events), Folder 20)
  - "Skills for Campus Organizing", Conference, March 1997, Conference Materials (Box 2 (3-Events), Folder 1)
  - "Skills for Campus Organizing", Conference, February 1998, Conference Materials (Box 2 (3-Events), Folder 2)
  - Social Forum Conference, 2004 (Box 2 (3-Events), Folder 3)
  - "Student Organizing Strategies", Conference, October 2002, Conference Materials (Box 2 (3-Events), Folder 4)
  - "Take the Power Back", Conference, October 2001, Conference Materials (Box 2 (3-Events), Folder 5)
  - "Training for Campus Activists", Workshop, 1992; Undated (Box 2 (3-Events), Folder 6)
  - "Uniting to Challenge Racism", Conference, February 2004, Conference Materials (Box 2 (3-Events), Folder 7)
  - "Uniting to Make a Change", Conference, Conference Materials, 1994 (Box 2 (3-Events), Folder 8)
  - "Becoming Anti-Racist Activists", Conference, Conference Flyer, 2002
  - "Becoming Anti-Racist Activists", Conference, Conference Flyer Text, 2002
  - "Becoming Anti-Racist Activists", Conference, Conference List, 2002
  - "Becoming Anti-Racist Activists", Conference, Conference Report, 2002
  - "Becoming Anti-Racist Activists", Conference, Conference Schedule, 2002
  - "Becoming Anti-Racist Activists", Conference, Flyer Email Version, 2002
  - "Becoming Anti-Racist Activists", Conference, Instructions For Breakout Group Facilitators, 2002
  - "Becoming Anti-Racist Activists", Conference, Panel Introduction Sheet, 2002
  - "Becoming Anti-Racist Activists", Conference, Press Release, 2002
  - "Becoming Anti-Racist Activists", Conference, Thank You Letter, 2002
  - "Building Strong Organizations", Conference, "America, Business As Usual" Image, 2003
  - "Building Strong Organizations", Conference, "Breaking The Chains", Image, 2003
  - "Building Strong Organizations", Conference, "Breaking The Chains, Bring The War Home", Image, 2002
  - "Building Strong Organizations", Conference, Building Strong Organizations Flyer, 2003
  - "Building Strong Organizations", Conference, Conference Flyer, 2003
  - "Building Strong Organizations", Conference, Conference Schedule, 2003
  - "Building Strong Organizations", Conference, Conference Schedule Facilitators, 2003
  - "Building Strong Organizations", Conference, "End The Slavery", Image, 2003
  - "Building Strong Organizations", Conference, Fall Conference List, 2003
  - "Building Strong Organizations", Conference, "Fighting Powers, Grassroots-Capital", Image, 2003
  - "Building the Peace Movement", Conference, Conference Email, 2003
  - "Building the Peace Movement", Conference, Facilitation Schedule For February 8 Inter, 2003
  - "Building the Peace Movement", Conference, Fall Conference List, 2003
  - "Building the Peace Movement", Conference, Flyer 2, 2003
  - "Building the Peace Movement", Conference, Schedule For Inter-Campus Anti-War Meeting, 2003
  - "Student Organization Strategies", Conference, Conference Flyer, 2002
  - "Student Organization Strategies", Conference, Conference List, 2002
  - "Student Organization Strategies", Conference, Conference Schedule, 2002
  - "Student Organization Strategies", Conference, Conference Schedule Facilitators, 2002
  - "Student Organization Strategies", Conference, Erica's Letter, 2002
  - "Take The Power Back", Conference, Attendees Fall Conference, 2001
  - "Take The Power Back", Conference, Campus Schedule -- Weekends Good For Conference, 2002
  - "Take The Power Back", Conference, Flyer, 2001
  - "Take The Power Back", Conference, Follow-up Letter, 2001
  - "Take The Power Back", Conference, Schedule, 2001
  - "Uniting To Challenge Racism", Conference, Conference Flyer, 2003